<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the confuter of Bellarmin's Second note of the church, antiquity, against the cavils of the adviser</title>
            <author>Tullie, George, 1652?-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7422</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13100324</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13100324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63840)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 402:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the confuter of Bellarmin's Second note of the church, antiquity, against the cavils of the adviser</title>
                  <author>Tullie, George, 1652?-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A defense of Simon Patrick's "The second note of the church examined."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Tullie. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, May 31, 1687. Hen. Maurice"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, --  Saint, 1542-1621. --  De notis ecclesiae.</term>
               <term>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707. --  Second note of the church examined, viz., Antiquity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97405:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE CONFUTER OF <hi>BELLARMIN's Second Note</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> ANTIQUITY, AGAINST THE CAVILS of the ADVISER.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
               <body>
                  <p>IMPRIMATUR, <hi>May</hi> 31. 1687.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HEN. MA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RICE.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard,</hi> MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:97405:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97405:2"/>
            <head>A Defence of the Confuter of <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Second Note of the Church, <hi>Antiquity,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I <hi>Apprehend</hi> by this Author's Genius, that <hi>'tis much eaſier</hi> for ſome Men to write <hi>Farce</hi> than <hi>Controverſy:</hi> And tho I cannot ſay whether or no any man ever undertook the Confutation of <hi>Bellarmin over a Pot,</hi> as our Author elegantly begins his Advice; yet he ſeems to me, by his ludicrous Behaviour, to have engaged in his Defence in that ſort of humour. He may think it <hi>Vanity,</hi> if he pleaſes, in the Reverend and Learned Author of the Piece he attaques, to aſſail the <hi>Roman Champion</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; yet even I, who never enter'd the <hi>Field of Controverſy</hi> before, ſhall preſume to engage with ſuch a <hi>Smatterer</hi> in the <hi>Noble Science,</hi> as his Second.</p>
            <p>And yet, immediately after this fit of Rhetorick, he do's not pretend, that the <hi>Pot</hi>-qualifications <hi>are the caſe of him who has undertaken to anſwer</hi> Bellarmin'<hi>s Marks of the Church.</hi> No, Why then do's he commence his Advice with ſuch a Suggeſtion? Did he think fit to publiſh to the World, that he had a mind to be impertinent? An humour, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in Conjunction with Buffoonry in ſerious Affairs, I would adviſe him againſt for the future, if <hi>the powerful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of an ill habit</hi> has not totally over-rul'd his Liberty in the matter.</p>
            <p>And thus, after the witty Introduction to his <hi>little good Will;</hi> little enough, I dare ſay; we come now to receive the Advice of this grave controverſial Counſellor, in the Caſe depending.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Then he pretends, (for I'le relate his Advice in ſhort-hand, as much as I can, till I find ſomething worth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97405:3"/> the tranſcribing) that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> never meant what his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary undertakes to prove, <hi>that the Plea of bare Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is proper to the Church:</hi> No! but this Gentleman muſt own that he did, when I have told him only, that by <hi>bare Antiquity,</hi> his Adverſary underſtands Antiquity abſtracted from the Conſideration of Truth, thoſe <hi>Ancient Truths</hi> deliver'd in the Scriptures. Now, I preſume, he will not ſay, that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> any where expreſly in his Book of Notes, muchleſs in this Chapter, makes the conſent of Doctrines with the written Word, which is not <hi>bare,</hi> but <hi>true Antiquity,</hi> a Note of the Church; tho indeed, ſuch is the force of Truth, he can hardly keep off of that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In his ninth Chapter, he makes agreement in Doctrine with the Ancient Church, a ſixth Note of the Church: Ancient, he farther explains by Apoſtolic; telling us likewiſe out of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> that a Church is ſo call'd, as for other Reaſons, ſo for her conſpiring with the Apoſtles in their Doctrines; and yet, after all, moſt pitifully ſlides off to quite another thing, as will appear to any one who ſhall examine that Chapter.</p>
            <p>But it may be almoſt worth a man's while to read the Adviſer's Comment upon <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Text, tho I hate tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing. <hi>He ſays, indeed,</hi> ſays my Author, <hi>that whoever at this time will find out the Catholick Church, profeſs'd in the Creed, amongſt ſo many pretenders, muſt not apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to any upſtart Congregation, which was never viſible in the World, but of late years; but to ſuch a Church which has been of as long ſtanding, as ever ſince Chriſt and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles days, and conſequently ſuch a Church to which Antiquity of neceſſity at this time belongs.</hi> This <hi>Bellarmin</hi> aſſerts.</p>
            <p>Where I obſerve, Firſt, that, by this laſt Expreſſion, he Repreſents his own flouriſhing Gloſs, as <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Words, which they are not; a thing that looks a little towards a deſign of putting a trick upon his Readers. <hi>2ly,</hi> That we are here ſhrewdly directed to find out the Catholick
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97405:3"/> Church by finding out a particular, to which we muſt ſtick without farther enquiry. <hi>3ly,</hi> That this Man paſſes <hi>a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ad genus,</hi> from Antiquity to <hi>Viſibility,</hi> which the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Logick of his Maſter <hi>Bellarmin</hi> would not probably have ſuffer'd him to have done. And laſtly, after all, that he unluckily ſays the ſame thing in ſubſtance, with what he diſproves in his Adverſary; for what do's all his Gloſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to, but to this; That he who would find out the true Church, muſt overlook all ſuch as boaſt not of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity at all adventures, without any regard had to the true Antiquity of their Doctrines, or any thing elſe they pretend to; and pitch upon that, without any more ado, <hi>which has been of as long ſtanding,</hi> (of as long ſtanding barely, without any farther reſpect) as ever ſince Chriſt and the Apoſtles days? And what is ſuch a <hi>ſtanding</hi> as this, but <hi>bare</hi> Antiquity? Unleſs he can prove a neceſſary entail of Truth upon a long Succeſſion, which all the World can never do. And therefore, hoping he may be a little more happy in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, than in giving Advice, I preſent him with his own, and the ſecond he gives; That when he would confute his Adverſary, he ſay not the ſame thing that he do's; and withal, deſire him to attend, for the future, more diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Senſe, than to the Expreſſion of a Period.</p>
            <p>But wherein do's the Confuter of <hi>Bellarmin</hi> thus unlucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly jump with him? Why, in explicating and proving the ſame Antiquity to be a Note of the Church, which <hi>Bellarmin</hi> affirms to be ſuch. To which I anſwer, firſt, that if <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> by Antiquity meant ſuch as his Confuter explains, <hi>p.</hi> 45. as is pretended, then he underſtood by that word, an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Doctrine with Chriſt and his Apoſtles, for ſo 'tis plain his Adverſary meant; but we have ſhown before, that that could not be <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Intention. <hi>2ly,</hi> That if the Cardinals Diſcourſe upon this Note do's really tend to prove, not <hi>Antiquity,</hi> (but as the Confuter compendiouſly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes, <hi>Priority</hi>) to belong to the Church, as it ſeems
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97405:4"/> to do; then 'tis demonſtrable to me, that he preſently grew weary of his Note, which he could not manage without blending and confounding it with another more proper and pertinent to his buſineſs, tho beſides his deſign.</p>
            <p>The third Inconſiſtency which he thinks he has found in the Confuter of <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> is this, That having prov'd <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> not to be a proper Note of the Church, becauſe it did not always belong to it, as a proper Characteriſtick of a thing ought to do, there being a time when the Church was <hi>new, p.</hi> 42. He ſhould, nothwiſtanding, in the 45 <hi>p.</hi> aſſert that the holy Scriptures are the <hi>true Antiquity,</hi> there being a time when they were <hi>new</hi> likewiſe; and here he thinks he has undoubtedly caught him. But alas, his Pen was more nimble than his thoughts were deep. If indeed <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Adverſary in this point had advanc'd this Propoſition, That Antiquity is a <hi>proper Note,</hi> or <hi>inſeparable Property</hi> of the Scriptures, or written Word, and had after this undertaken to prove, that Antiquity could not be ſuch a Note of the Church, becauſe the Church was once <hi>new;</hi> the Argument would with equal force have recoil'd upon that ſame Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his in relation to the Scriptures. Or if <hi>Bell.</hi> had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd only that the Church <hi>is truely Ancient,</hi> and his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary had denied it upon the Score of its former <hi>newneſs;</hi> he could not neither, if his own Objection were good, have rightly affirm'd that the Ss. are the <hi>true Antiquity:</hi> But who can diſcover the leaſt repugnancy betwixt theſe two Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that Antiquity is a <hi>Note</hi> of the Church, and conſequently, as the Confuter well argues, proper to it, and inſeparable from it, which yet cannot be true, if the Church was once <hi>new;</hi> and this, that the Scriptures are the <hi>true Antiquity;</hi> i. e. that the Doctrines deliver'd in the Scripures or written Word, are the oldeſt and trueſt Doctrines in the Chriſtian Church. Thus I have often obſerv'd, that a few plain Words will unriddle great Myſteries in appearance; and that ſome Men are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily apt to run away with a bare jingle of Words, inſtead of harmony in Senſe.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97405:4"/>
            <p>In the fourth Remark we meet with no leſs a charge than that of a contradiction; and that's a bad buſineſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in ſo narrow a compaſs of Pages; but where has this ſtarter of difficulties eſpied it, for 'tis not eaſily diſcernable? Why, the Confuter of <hi>Bellarmin</hi> has <hi>aſſerted abſolutely,</hi> p. 42. That Antiquity is not a proper note of the Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>p. 45. He has found out an Antiquity that is proper to the Church.</hi> In good time! <hi>Bellarmin</hi> uſes the word equivocally, either for that which is <hi>ancient,</hi> or for that which is <hi>firſt;</hi> the former his Confuter ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 42. is not a Note proper to the Church; but that the latter, which <hi>Bellarmin</hi> did not originally mean by his Note of Antiquity, tho he was forc'd to run into it, belongs to the Church. And is this now <hi>ad idem?</hi> and if not, where's the contradiction? If, diſcourſing with this Gentleman, I ſhould own my ſelf a Member of the Catholick Church, and finding afterwards that, according to their uſual and preſumptuous blunder, by the Catholick Church he meant the Roman Catholick Church, I ſhould deny my ſelf to be a Member of it, ſhould I be guilty of a Contradiction? for ſhame what tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling is this? I thought ſome ſort of People had better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the dubious import of Words uſed <hi>equivocally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His fifth Remark wants nothing but Truth to make it a very good one; and is this, That the Confuter of <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> has produced a Citation out of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> which is ſo far <hi>from favouring his own Cauſe, that it really ſupports his Adverſaries, and is the very ground of what they maintain, and he oppoſes.</hi> And in earneſt then, amongſt ſuch great variety, he was very unhappy in his choice. But how does the Adviſer make this appear? why, by two or three pert Interogations, and that's all. To which if I oppoſed only as many more, I might reaſonably ſeem to have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him a juſt Anſwer. For the place is ſo extremely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the Argument the Confuter was upon, that, for my own part, I can ſcarce perſwade my ſelf the Adviſer
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97405:5"/> was in earneſt when he made his Remark, if he knew what he was about. The Confuter was ſhowing, that bare Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, as before explained, could not be a proper Criterion to judge of the true Church by, for that, amongſt other Reaſons, wicked Doctrines running down to Poſterity, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from the Infancy of the Goſpel, made uſe at length of the Plea of Antiquity to give them countenance and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; which pretence, ſays he, was notwithſtanding refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Fathers in ſeveral remarkable Words. Amongſt others of which he alledges that paſſage in St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Pompeius. Cuſtom without truth is but Antiquity of error—and there is a ſhort way of Religious and ſimple minds to find out what is truth; for if we return to the beginning and original of Divine Tradition, Humane Error ceaſes—Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let us return to our Lords Original, the Evangelical Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, the Apoſtolical Tradition,</hi> &amp;c. Is not now <hi>our Lord's Original, the Evangelical Beginning</hi> (terms ſynonimous with <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition</hi>) that <hi>ancient Truth</hi> the Confuter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to appeal to? Or, is this, as the Adviſer farther boaſts, <hi>That ſetting up the very Tradition which Catholicks appeal to?</hi> Yes, ſays he. But why ſo? for no other reaſon doubtleſs but becauſe he luckily eſpied the Word <hi>Tradition</hi> in that ſentence, and perhaps found it under that head in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-place Book. Now ſeriouſly, if this Gentleman pleaſes, I'le produce him half an hundred Inſtances out of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, <hi>Irenaeus, Tertullian, Cyprian,</hi> &amp;c. where <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> is uſed by them for the Scriptures, or written Word of God. If he had but conſulted that other Epiſtle to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius,</hi> Cited by the Confuter in his Margent, he would have found it taken there five or ſix times in that very ſenſe; and that 'tis really ſo in the place now before us, is ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrably evident from the Epiſtle whence it is cited, that none who had ever conſulted the Original, could with the leaſt modeſty, or judgment, have alledged it in Defence of Tradition, as ſtated in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97405:5"/> Holy Martyr refuting here what Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> had replied to him in a Letter concerning the Baptiſm of Hereticks, repeats ſeveral Paſſages of it. Of which this is one, <hi>Si quis ergo a quacunque Haereſi venerit ad nos, nihil innovetur niſi quod Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum eſt, ut manus illi imponatur in poenitentiam.</hi> To which St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> immediately replies, <hi>Whence is this Tradition? does it deſcend from the Authority of our Lord and the Goſpel, or from the Injunctions and Epiſtles of the Apoſtles? For God teſtifies, That thoſe things are to be done which are written. If therefore it be commanded either in the Goſpel, or in the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, or in the Acts, that they who come from any Hereſie over to the Church, be not Baptized, but only have impoſition of hands for repentance; let this Divine and Holy Tradition be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. But if,</hi> &amp;c. And now what thinks our Adviſer of St. <hi>Cyprian's Apoſtolical Tradition,</hi> which pleaſed him ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully at firſt ſight, and I dare ſay he never look'd farther? Are the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Acts,</hi> the only <hi>Tradition</hi> which Catholicks appeal to? Let him remember his <hi>Trent</hi>-Creed, and then tell me.</p>
            <p>We come now, in the next place, to his Remarks and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in relation to the Confuter's ſecond Propoſition, That the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> vainly pretends to true Antiquity, <hi>i. e.</hi> ancient Truth. And here we find him all on a ſudden ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a very ſtrong fit of the Gentleman; he's upon his Punctilio's, and teaching his Adverſary <hi>better manners</hi> than to charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Lyes;</hi> and yet this Maſter of Controverſial Ceremonies is off of his breeding within two Pages after, where we have him ranking <hi>the Divines and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putants of the Church of</hi> England <hi>with honeſt Coblers and Tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> as if they were really at a Club together over the <hi>Pot</hi> he ſpeaks of in his Introduction, for the Confutation of <hi>Bellarmin;</hi> and, to inſtance no farther in this fulſome kind, what elſe is his whole ſcribble but one continued breach <hi>of Good Manners and common Civiliey,</hi> unleſs he thinks it the part of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to Boffoon a whole Church, and all her Clergy? I ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97405:6"/> not farther recriminate, though I juſtly might, from ſeveral of their late Papers, were it worth the while. I ſhall only there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tell him, that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> in that very Chapter we are now upon, gives his Adverſaries the <hi>Lye</hi> twice very roundly; and why ſhould he be angry with a man for copying after ſuch an Original? And that I could wiſh ſome People were not ſo deeply concern'd in the Character of thoſe who, in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's homely <hi>Phraſe,</hi> ſhall in the latter times ſpeak <hi>Lyes</hi> in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie [1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2.] and by <hi>lying Wonders</hi> [2 Theſſ. 2. 9.] impoſe upon the People, as to deſerve ſuch <hi>plain Engliſh.</hi> But the Lye deſerves a Stab, they ſay, and therefore we may now expect a keen Pen, when pointed with ſuch generous Reſentments.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place therefore he pretends, that the Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>in kicking down the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>has overthrown his own at the ſame blow.</hi> For he having aſſerted, <hi>p.</hi> 49. [not, as the Adviſer words it, <hi>That the addition of Articles to the ancient Creed, takes of all claim to the ancient Truth,</hi> as if a Church that coins new and falſe Articles of Faith, does thereby for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit her Title to thoſe true and ancient ones ſhe before retain'd, though not impugn'd by theſe new ones, as the Adviſer would ſuggeſt, but] that the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> having ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added ſeveral Articles of her own, contrary to ſeveral of thoſe Chriſtian Truths upon which ſhe was originally founded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes another Church from what ſhe was then, and cannot plead Antiquity for her preſent Conſtitution; the Adviſer ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes, that neither then can the Church of <hi>England</hi> be the ancient Church, <hi>who beſides the Nicene and Athanaſian Creeds, has another of a later date, of nine and thirty Articles, beſides another Plot-Creed call'd the Teſt.</hi> Sure this Man wrote only to make People merry. Or, is he really not able to diſtinguiſh betwixt Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, of neceſſity to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd in order to Salvation, and ſuch he cannot but know the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> accounts all the Articles of the new <hi>Trent</hi> Creed, and thoſe of <hi>Communion</hi> and external agreement,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97405:6"/> which, tho <hi>ancient Truths,</hi> (and if we cannot give better proofs of their <hi>true</hi> Antiquity than they can do of their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Articles, wee'l be content to loſe them) are yet of an inferior Nature. And as to our <hi>Plot Creed</hi> in particular, I'le ſet another <hi>Plot-Creed</hi> with a Witneſs againſt it; and that is, the <hi>depoſing Power,</hi> by <hi>Law eſtabliſh'd,</hi> by a Law that's a Creed in the ſtricteſt Senſe to them, the Definition of a General Council; and had it not been for this, and other <hi>Plot-Creeds</hi> of abſolving Subjects from their Allegiance, and the like, I am apt to believe they had never been troubled with ours.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph the Adviſer leads us ſuch a Dance, there's no keeping Pace with him. He frisks and frolicks it ſo in his <hi>Field of Crontroverſy,</hi> that he puts me in mind of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of another ſort of Animal, lately come into a good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and in a warm Sun. I was in deſpair for ſome time of finding out his meaning in his long Ramble of two Pages, but beating about, for it laid in a very narrow compaſs, I found it at laſt in a Corner of the <hi>Field of Controverſy;</hi> and 'tis in ſhort, this, That the Confuter's Argumentation, which ſee <hi>p.</hi> 50. &amp;c. do's not prove that when a <hi>Change</hi> or <hi>Alteration</hi> in Religion begins <hi>publickly</hi> to be <hi>abetted, maintained</hi> and <hi>propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>That then ſuch an Alteration in Religion could ſpread it ſelf over the whole Chriſtian World, and yet the Authors, Promoters, Abetters, and Embracers of it, not be known, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of.</hi> This being a popular, tho very weak refuge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon by greater men than the Adviſer, I ſhall give it a more diſtinct, tho ſhort, Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then I ſay, That the Confuter, <hi>p.</hi> 52. has given him one particular Inſtance of an <hi>acknowledg'd Change,</hi> of which they themſelves cannot yet aſſign the Author by whom, nor the time when, it was introduc'd; and that he has farther, <hi>p.</hi> 53, &amp;c. as much as his deſign'd Brevity would admit, evinc'd the Riſe and Progreſs of two notorious changes in Religion, eſtabliſh'd in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Oppoſition they met with, and could at h pleaſure have farther enlarg'd upon this Subject.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97405:7"/>
            <p>Now either of theſe <hi>Ratiocinations</hi> are a ſufficient Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s, adopted by the Adviſer; And how little he has replied to his Inſtances, we ſhall ſee by and by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> He is mightily out in his Computation, unleſs the old blunder of the <hi>Roman</hi> being the Catholick Church, run ſtill in his Head; if he thinks all thoſe Doctrines of theirs, which we charge with the want of true Antiquity, were ever univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiv'd <hi>over the whole Chriſtian World,</hi> as he flouriſhes to exaggerate the Matter; What thinks he of one of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futer's inſtances, the Papal Authority, to go no further? But I hope his better Knowledg in this point will ſuperſede me the labour of enlarging upon ſo copious an Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> I muſt tell the Adviſer, that the Doctrines we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, being generally ſuch as are calcuted for the Meridian of <hi>Rome,</hi> the greater Veneration, Wealth, and Grandeur of the Pope and his Clergy; 'tis no wonder at all that we hear not of ſo much Buſtle and Noiſe about them in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> World, as we might otherwiſe have expected. And if he asks me, as he's good at ſuch ſilly queſtions, <hi>Where the Church of</hi> England <hi>was all this time, and why She did not Preach, and make Laws againſt ſuch Corruptions and their Abetters;</hi> I preſume to ask his Wiſdom again, Where She was under the late Reign of <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and why She did not Preach and make <hi>Laws</hi> againſt him and his Abetters.</p>
            <p>Why truly She was, in both Caſes, under the invincible Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of an Uſurper; and therefore, methinks, the general Anſwer of the Houſholder to his Servants, asking him whence came the tares, that an Enemy had Sown them, might ſatisfie in this Anti-tipe of the Parable likewiſe; eſpecially, ſince we find neither Maſter nor Servants any farther ſollicitous in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Enquiries about them, even when they <hi>grew up,</hi> and <hi>were</hi> conſequently <hi>ſeen and diſcern'd;</hi> for ill weeds to be ſure grow faſt enough. And I ſhall only in this place, deſire the Gentlemen, who are ſo ready to boaſt of the preſent Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the diſcriminating Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97405:7"/> notwithſtanding the Oppoſition they have met with, to make this farther Remark with me upon the Parable of the Tares, <hi>That they were ſuffer'd to grow up with the Wheat until the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt,</hi> and let them recollect what became of them then.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> Were there no other method for Errors to ſpread in the Church, than by what the Adviſer ſeems to Dream of, <hi>by appearing in open Contradiction and Defiance to the true Church, condemning its Doctrine, and oppoſing the Articles of her Faith, as Erroneous and Heretical,</hi> as he tragically expreſſes it; then his inference might probably hold good, unleſs we will ſuppoſe ſuch Errors to have appear'd in a very dark and ſupine Age in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and even in a more cautious, 'tis poſſible Records might be loſt; but alas, ſince they uſally grow up and advance after a quite different manner, <hi>pedetentim,</hi> by little and little, as <hi>Fiſher</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> owns the Doctrine of Purgatory did; or, it may be under the Colour of greater Piety and Devotion, or the like, as the Doctrines of Image and Saint-worſhip, and thereby draw in the Paſtors of the Church themſelves for their <hi>Maintainers</hi> and <hi>Abetters;</hi> his Argumentation falls to the Ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>5thly,</hi> He ought to diſtinguiſh betwixt ſuch Errors, as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately confront the prime Foundations of the Chriſtian Faith, and that Apoſtaſy the Spirit hath foretold ſhould be brought in by ſuch as ſpeak lies in Hypocriſy, [1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1, 2.] of the firſt ſort were the early Hereſies, concerning the Perſon of our Saviour, His Divinity and Humanity, The Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body, and the like; ſuch as theſe indeed did not, nor cannot well be ſuppos'd to appear in the Church without a mark upon the time of their riſe, their <hi>Authors</hi> and open <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracers.</hi> The other is a myſtery of Iniquity, and may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd by ſpecious and almoſt imperceptible methods, as is hinted above, without any great ſtir or din about them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>6thly,</hi> To the ſingle Inſtance of the Confuter concerning an acknowledg'd change, the riſe whereof they themſelves cannot account for, the half Communion, I ſhall add two more, the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97405:8"/> Doctrines of Purgatory and Indulgences, both own'd by <hi>Fiſher</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> to be of uncertain Original; thereby acknowledging them not to be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe <hi>Ancient Truths</hi> we contend for, and yet are not able to tell who firſt brought them in. To his two Inſtances of <hi>Alteration</hi> in Religion, the Papal Authority, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images, which we can account for according to the Adviſer's Directions, I add one more; The great Burning Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Tranſubſtantiation; whoſe Riſe, Progreſs and Oppoſers, they have lately been told of, [<hi>See Diſc. againſt Tranſubſt.</hi>] re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the Adviſer to <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> for farther Inſtruction in this matter, if he deſires it. After all which, I muſt farther pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume briefly to remind him of the ſeveral new Definitions of the <hi>Trent</hi> Council, and of others, which from Doctrines formerly taught, ſprang up preſently, in that prolifick Soil of Religion, into Articles of Faith; and ſure 'tis a conſiderable <hi>Alteration in Religion,</hi> to make the belief of Points neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which were not ſo before. And yet I hope we are able to name the <hi>who,</hi> the <hi>where,</hi> and the <hi>when,</hi> of thoſe Alterations. But</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I muſt tell the Adviſer, that, tho out of complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance to him and his Betters, I have ſo far enlarg'd upon this Argument; yet, as ſtated by himſelf, with reference to the <hi>publick Appearance</hi> of Corruptions; 'tis anſwer'd in one word, by the ſame curt Ratiocination as it was before, when conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd with Relation to their <hi>firſt riſe</hi> only. For, tho we could give no account of the <hi>open Maintainers, Embracers</hi> and <hi>Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> nor of the <hi>Oppoſers</hi> of any Doctrine or Practice prevailing in the preſent Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet, if we are able to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that ſuch Doctrine or Practice manifeſtly differs from what was at firſt eſtabliſh'd in the Church by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; or going yet farther, can ſhow out of unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Records, that no ſuch thing, as for inſtance, the preſent Papal Authority, was ever own'd in the Church for ſuch a time, 600 years for example; do's it not inevitably follow,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97405:8"/> That a change however has been made, both from the <hi>true Antiquity,</hi> the Scriptures, and the ſubordinate Antiquity of ſo many Centuries of the Church, tho we could not name the place where, the time when, and the Perſons by whom, ſuch Corruptions were publickly maintained and abetted? I can ſcarce, for my own part, believe that men are in earneſt, when they oppoſe ſuch a wretched piece of Sophiſtry to the unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable argument of matter of Fact, and the plaineſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in the World.</p>
            <p>We come now to his Remark upon the Confuter's inſtance of Communion in one kind, and his advice to him here is, to prove in his next, <hi>That a diverſity of practiſe is an alteration in Religion; and eſpecially of ſuch a practiſe, which Chriſt left indifferent in reſpect of the Laity, and without any poſitive com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their receiving it in both kinds.</hi> But ſince he has not thought fit to prove this at all, which was his proper pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince in this place, unleſs by two or three frivolous Citations, of which afterwards; I ſhall ſtill take the contrary for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being well aſſured, firſt, That he can ſhow no poſitive command to the Clergy to receive it in both kinds, which does not equally include the Laiety; and, ſecondly, That they, being equally intereſted with the Clergy in the benefits that accrue to mankind from the effuſion of our Saviour's Blood, and the Sacrament of the Euchariſt being inſtituted in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of this effuſion of his Blood, as well as of the breaking of his Body; the drinking of the Cup, as well as the eating of the Bread, becomes as neceſſary a part of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in relation to the Laiety, as it is to the Clergy; they who equally partake of the benefits of both, being equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Commemoration of both. And a thouſand years conſtant practice accordingly, is a good expoſition of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Deſign in the inſtitution; and can then <hi>the refuſing the Cup</hi> to the Laiety be called a <hi>diverſity of Practice</hi> only of <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring it</hi> to them? Or, is the <hi>aboliſhing</hi> of a practice (of ſuch Divine Authority, and of ſo long a continuance in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97405:9"/> Univerſal Church) in relation to ſuch Myriads of People, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a differing <hi>modus</hi> of <hi>exerciſing</hi> it? A familiar Inſtance will illuſtrate the matter, though it ſeems ſufficiently to diſcover it ſelf by its own natural abſurdity. Suppoſe then ſome friend of the Adviſers ſhould, by his laſt Will and Teſtament, leave ſo much Beer, and ſo much Bread, to be diſtributed every Week, for inſtance, to the Poor of the Pariſh where he had lived; and the Adviſer, his Executor, ſhould, for a long time, take care to have both the Beer and the Bread faithfully diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted according to the Teſtator's Will; but yet, at laſt, for ſome private reaſon of his own, ſhould deprive them of their portion of Beer, and confine them to Bread only; does he imagine he could ſham off the Wotld, and the Poor People concern'd, with this piece of Sophiſtry, That what he did was only <hi>a diverſity of Practice</hi> in fulfilling the Will of the Deceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and no <hi>alteration</hi> of the Will it ſelf? Who ſees not, at firſt ſight, the illuſion of ſuch an evaſion? But now becauſe the Adviſer counſels the Confuter to prove in his next, That <hi>a diverſity of Practice,</hi> as he pleaſantly calls the denial of the Cup, is an <hi>alteration in Religion;</hi> I'le endeavour to do it for him, in as few words as I can, now that I am upon the ſpot, and ſave him the labour. For, if the Sacrament of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt be a part of the Chriſtian Religion, and I hope 'twill be granted to be a very conſiderable one, and the Cup an eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part of that Sacrament; then they who deprive the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of the Cup, the <hi>diverſity of Practice</hi> here ſpoke of, make thereby an alteration in Religion; but, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I'le make good this Argumentation to him when he pleaſes. The cuſtom of adminiſtring the Cup with Water only inſtead of Wine, was not, I hope, ſo great a <hi>diverſity of Practice,</hi> as not admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Cup at all to the Laiety, who were at that time par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Cup, ſuch as it was; and yet it were worth his while to read what ſtreſs St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> in his 63 <hi>Ep.</hi> to <hi>Caecilius,</hi> lays upon the <hi>practice</hi> of our Lord in his Inſtitution of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. And, in a word, ſo far is this defrauding the Laiety
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97405:9"/> of the Cup, from being no <hi>alteration in Religion,</hi> that, beſides what has been ſaid, it opens wide the Door to the greateſt <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations</hi> imaginable. For, if the Church, nay, what is worſe, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in particular, can, by her own tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prerogative, <hi>alter</hi> and act contrary to this poſitive Law and Inſtitution of Chriſt, ſhe may, by the ſame reaſon, diſpence with, or formally abrogate any of the other at her pleaſure. As for his Quotations out of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Melancthon,</hi> I have not been able to find, upon a pretty diligent ſearch, as much as the very Tract and Epiſtles from whence he cites them, and therefore am apt to imagine, that taking them up at ſecond hand, he, or his Author, made a miſtake in them. However it be, it matters not much; for his ſecond Citation out of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther</hi> appears, at firſt ſight, ſo forreign to his purpoſe, that by it we may gueſs at the reſt. But above all, recommend me to the Skull which could Cite that place of <hi>Spalaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> l. 5. c. 6. for the refuſal of the Cup; or conclude, that becauſe private Perſons, upon <hi>extraordinary</hi> occaſions, as want of Wine, antipathy to it, or the like, mentioned by this very Author, may lawfully receive in one kind, the Church may make an univerſal ſtanding Law againſt the Laiety's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving in both. Give me leave but juſt to continue the words of <hi>Spalatenſis,</hi> where the Adviſer leaves of, and you will be ſufficiently able to pronounce of either the judgment or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity of this Author, without any farther deſcant upon him. After having told us then in the general, in what caſes the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament may be lawfully received under the ſpecies of Bread alone, he proceeds, <hi>Though in ſuch a caſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not truly and properly whole. Wine may either be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or the Perſon abſtemious;</hi> or, <hi>it may be more convenient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieve at home, than in the Church, upon a lawful cauſe, in which caſe a man may carry the Bread along with him, tho not ſo conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently the Wine, as old examples teach us</hi> (a practice perhaps not altogether warrantable in the Church) <hi>But the Church neither could, nor can, by an univerſal Law deprive the Laiety of the Cup,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97405:10"/> whether they will or no, upon no neceſſity at all; for what Christ granted to all men, is in vain denied by the Church; and where the whole Sacrament may and ought to be exhibited, it cannot be mutilated and halfed without the greateſt injuſtice; and this is expreſly prohibited under an Anathema by</hi> Gelaſius <hi>in a Canon of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph, the Adviſer is all upon the ramble again, and you ſcarce know where to have him; I'le pick up the ſenſe tho' he has dropt here and there, and digeſt it for him as well as I can. Firſt, Then he is angry with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futer for dateing the riſe of the Papal Authority he ſpeaks of, ſo far back as Pope <hi>Victor;</hi> and his reaſon is, <hi>becauſe the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is generally believ'd to have been in thoſe days pure and uncorrupt.</hi> Here wants nothing but a good conſequence. The Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was then ſound and Orthodox, and therefore one of her Biſhops could not be of a warm, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate, or aſſuming temper, as <hi>Africans</hi> generally are, of which Country he was; and, by an unwarrantable action, undeſignedly perhaps, lay the firſt Foundation of a future en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment and uſurpation. This is the whole Logic of the Buſineſs. But, the practiſes the Confuter cenſures, were <hi>own'd by the Chriſtians of thoſe days.</hi> I wonder then he did not ſhow the vanity of what the Confuter alledges concerning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primand that <hi>Celeſtine</hi> met with from the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his intruſion into their Affairs; or, to go farther back, did the Adviſer never hear of the buſtle that Victor's excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the <hi>Aſiatic</hi> Biſhops made in the Church? Or was no Body ever ſo kind as to tell him how ill that action was reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Biſhops of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church it ſelf; as may appear from a fragment of a Letter of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> to <hi>Victor</hi> upon this occaſion? [ſee <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Hiſt. l. 5. c. 24.] But, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Pope <hi>Victor</hi>'s practiſe could be no other than an <hi>Apoſtolical truth, becauſe he lived in the Second Century.</hi> I thought we ſhould have him upon the Argument of <hi>bare An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity,</hi> for all his former indignation at the Confuter for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97405:10"/> him 'twas <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s ſecond Note of the Church; and here again is nothing but the poor buſineſs of a little Logic, and concluſiveneſs wanting. For the argument proves too much, and ſo proves nothing at all to his purpoſe, being that which <hi>a fortiori</hi> will juſtifie the Treachery of <hi>Judas,</hi> and all the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Doctrines that were broach'd before <hi>Victor</hi>'s time. But I need not farther expoſe its abſurdity, the Confuter having done it ſo excellently well in his firſt particular. His third ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of reaſon, is, that the Popes the Confuter mentions as beginners of the preſent Innovation of the Papal Authority, living before or in the time of the four firſt General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, if what is pretended were true, thoſe Councils would have taken notice of it. Now becauſe he confines his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to thoſe Councils only, ſo ſhall I do my anſwer, which need be no other than this, That the Innovation was then perfectly in its Infancy; the Tares as yet, according to his own diſtinction, in the dark and under ground, not grown up, and overtopping the Corn, as they did afterwards, and therefore difficultly perceptible, at leaſt in their future fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal tendency and event; and as ſuch might, conſequently, eaſily eſcape the ſevere and ſolemn Animadverſion of a general Council. But can the Adviſer imagin, that if the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> had, in thoſe days, preſumed to have broke down all the ancient mounds and boundaries of Juriſdiction, the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and had, in a word, but offer'd at ſuch an audacious attempt as an univerſal Monarchy over the whole Church of Chriſt, that they would not have been <hi>taken notice of by</hi> thoſe Councils, as they were by others after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and by the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops during that time? Yes, he may aſſure himſelf we ſhould have had a brand of Infamy ſet upon them, that would have laſted to all Poſterity, if any but the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had the keeping of the Records. But there's ſomething behind ſtill in this Paragraph, which looks, as if he were fond of it; &amp; therefore we muſt do it the civility of a remark; and that is, <hi>that the ancient Fathers urge the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97405:11"/> ſucceſſion of theſe very Biſhops of</hi> Rome, <hi>as an Argument of the True Orthodox Faith and Religion profeſſed in that Church. Ergo,</hi> What? What you pleaſe. I have told this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman before, that the Orthodoxy of the Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in thoſe days is no way concern'd in the preſent debate; for the Church over which the Biſhops we ſpeak of, preſided, might be ſound in the Faith; for the Pope's univerſal Juriſdiction was then no Article of it; and yet they, through paſſion, inadvertency, or perhaps natural ambition, lay the firſt Foundation of that monſtrous Fabric of Papal power, that after-Ages built upon it. I ſhall not here enter upon a Diſcourſe concerning the proof of the Truth of Doctrines by ſucceſſion of Biſhops, becauſe the Adviſer uſes it only as a <hi>Medium</hi> to prove, tho' poor man he has made but bad uſe of it, that no Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> could by any means ſow thoſe Seeds, which might be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards improv'd into dangerous innovations; yet, I muſt tell him that, after all, thoſe Fathers <hi>ultimately</hi> reſolve the truth of all Doctrines into their harmony and agreement with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolic writings. The ridiculous Buffoonry that fills up the reſt of the Paragraph, ſufficiently expoſes its Author, of it ſelf; only whereas he tells us, we have no other way to look <hi>fair,</hi> than by <hi>blackning</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> I muſt tell him in return, That, in my Mind, they are equally impertinent who would waſh an <hi>Aethiopian</hi> white, and who would paint him blacker than he is.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph about Image-worſhip, he palliates very finely, as if Paint and Varniſh were ſtill as requiſite to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon that indefenſible Subject, as to the Subject it ſelf. The Confuter hinting briefly to him by what advances Image-worſhip crept up to that height, wherein 'tis now taught and practic'd in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> begins as he ought, from the very firſt Steps, or unhappy Occaſions only, of that religious Worſhip that was afterwards given them; <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> uſe of them 300 years after Chriſt, improv'd into the <hi>Rhetorical,</hi> as he well expreſſes it, in 300 years more after that. Now upon
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97405:11"/> this faſtens the Adviſer, without ever taking notice of the Religious Adoration that is paid them, that great <hi>Alteration of Religion</hi> the Confuter complains of, and of which the former uſes of them were only unhappily Introductory; but ſlurs it over in the general terms of <hi>other Reaſons;</hi> others with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for which the Confuter <hi>condemns the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>of Innovation in Religion.</hi> Is this Ingenuity? Is this Arguing? But alas, 'tis as good as the Cauſe will bear. How then is the <hi>Church of</hi> England <hi>laid upon her back</hi> by the Alteration in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the Confuter in this place charges upon the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Do's the Church of <hi>England</hi> worſhip Images? If not, She can never be in the ſame Condemnation, for not worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, with that Church, which doth worſhip them. But here perhaps lies the Myſtery; Mr. <hi>Mountague,</hi> in the 21. Chap. of his Appeal to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> approves of the giving them [<hi>Civil] Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Reverence, as was done by Pope</hi> Gregory <hi>in Rememo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and more effectual Repreſentment of the Prototype;</hi> all which amounts to no more, even in his own Expoſition in that Chap. than to a bare <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> uſe of them; And what of all this? Do's it hence follow that the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> is equally <hi>laid on her Back</hi> with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly worſhips them? Is there no difference betwixt Mr. <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague</hi>'s private Opinion, and the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> No difference betwixt a meer <hi>Hiſtorical,</hi> and that <hi>Religious</hi> uſe that is made of them in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Well, but Mr. <hi>Mountague</hi> confeſſes that the Hiſtorical and Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical uſes of them, are allow'd by the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And ſuppoſe ſo for once; what becomes of the poor Conſequence ſtill, for that's what I am concern'd for? The Church of <hi>England</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows an uſe of Images harmleſs in it ſelf, and therefore She is equally culpable with a Church that allows, nay commands, an uſe of them, ſinful in it ſelf. Conſquences ſo big with Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that a man needs but name them, to expoſe them. But after all, the Church of <hi>England</hi> has no ſuch Doctrine that I know of, nor do's Mr. <hi>Mountague</hi> ſay ſo. He ſays indeed, Chap. 20. that we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97405:12"/> do not account the Papiſts Idolatrous for theſe Hiſtorical and Rhetorical uſes of them; and in the ſame Chap. that it is not the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to have departed from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> about this point, if She had gone no farther in Practice nor Precept than what St. <hi>Gregory</hi> recommended; and that he, for his part, could have actually gone thus far along with them: But he affirms no ſuch thing of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as the Adviſer would make him. But, ſince he has been pleas'd to make uſe of Mr. <hi>Mountague</hi>'s Name, as a ſort of an Abetter of their Doctrino in this Point: I think I cannot do Him, nor the Reader, greater Juſtice, than here to give a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimen of his Senſe of this <hi>Doctrine and Practice</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Thus, then, ſays he in the 19. Chap. one of thoſe ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Author. <hi>I do not, I cannot, I will not deny that Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is groſly committed in the Church of</hi> Rome. <hi>The ruder ſort at leaſt are not excuſable, who go to it with down-right Idolatry, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any relative Adoration, worſhipping that which they behold with their Eyes. This Idolatry is Ancient in their</hi> Schools, as he there ſhews; not amongſt the Vulgar only.</p>
            <p>The little Flouriſhes which follow, are not worth a remark; for who ſays, That ſuch an uſe of Images, as he there ſpeaks of, <hi>leaves the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>without all title to Antiquity,</hi> or, that <hi>it <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchurches her?</hi> This I am ſure is a <hi>Rhetorical</hi> uſe of words, inſtead of a <hi>Logical</hi> one, which obliges a Diſputant to keep to his terms; a ſtrictneſs, alas, that will never agree with thin Senſe, and a bad Cauſe. The Confutation of his Compariſon betwixt the Introduction of the worſhip of Images, and <hi>Lawn-ſleeves,</hi> &amp;c. I leave to the Laughter or Indignation of every Reader, as he is in Humour, when he meets with it; for he who would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe ſuch ſtuff any other Reply, might juſtly be thought guilty of as great trifling in refuting, as he in advancing it.</p>
            <p>His Remarks upon the Confuter's Concluſion, are a pure Declamation, and I have no great appetite to encounter a School-Boys Exerciſe. He tells us, <hi>He cannot poſſibly make ſenſe</hi> of what the Confuter ſays in reference to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97405:12"/> That her Religion, by Law eſtabliſhed, is the true Primitive Chriſtianity;</hi> for ſo run his Words; and what then? Is the Confuter bound to find him in underſtanding? He might have enough to do at that rate. I thought he had explain'd himſelf in the next Page, and that very pertinently too, by telling him, That our Religion is as old as Chriſt and his Apoſtles, with whom whoſoever agrees, they are truly <hi>ancient</hi> Churches, tho of no longer ſtanding than yeſterday: As they that diſagree with them, are <hi>new,</hi> tho they can run up their Pedigree to the very Apoſtles; and this he farther confirms by <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Authority. Now if the Adviſer had had a mind, or ability, to have ſpoke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently to the matter in hand, he ſhould have endeavour'd to have ſhewn, either, that Conformity with Primitive and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolic Doctrine does not make a Church truly Ancient and Apoſtolic; or, that the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Engl.</hi> have no ſuch Conformity; for if they have, 'twill be found that Chriſt and his Apoſtles <hi>have a greater hand</hi> in the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Church, than in that of <hi>Rome,</hi> notwithſtanding his trifling harangue to the contrary. <hi>The World knows very well,</hi> he tells us, <hi>when this Church was firſt eſtabliſh'd by Law;</hi> and ſo does the World know too, when Chriſtianity was firſt ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Throne, and protected by the ſecular arm, and yet I believe the Chriſtians of thoſe days thought no worſe of their Religion for that; nor, I believe, would the Adviſer think worſe of his, if the Laws were on its ſide. <hi>But where this Church was before 'twas eſtabliſh'd by Law, that is not ſo eaſie to tell.</hi> Why, truly in my mind, 'twas much in the ſame ſtate with the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church under the Dominion of <hi>Pharoah</hi> in <hi>Aegypt;</hi> the one being born down and enſlaved by a Temporal Tyranny; the other by both a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Spiritual Uſurpation; till God was pleaſed, as to reſcue the one, ſo the other too, out of the Houſe of Bondage. After this, he whiſſles and plays about the <hi>ſeparation and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty</hi> of this Church. To which I ſhall only return; That if he pleaſes to be but ſo kind to himſelf and to us, as to lay aſide
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97405:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Buffoon and Declamator for a while, and condeſcend, for once, to ſpeak to the purpoſe, upon that, or any other ſubject; he needs not fear a ſuitable reply from ſome or other. In the laſt place, he is for finding out the Confuter ſome work, in Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the proof of our adequate belief of the Creed, <hi>and in the ſame ſenſe, in which it was taught by the Apoſtles, and profeſſed by the Primitive Church.</hi> No man, who knows the Reverend and Learned. Confuter, can doubt of his Abilities for a much harder Task than what the Adviſer would ſet him; but I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume he knows how to diſpoſe of his time much better than to lay it out in refuting the Suggeſtions of every incompetent Adverſary; and ſince he has thought fit to fling out this Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe about the belief of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> in my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion 'twould much more become him to make it out in the firſt place, and then, perhaps he may hear of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futer, if he chances to write any thing worth his Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>He tells us, in one place, of the forwardneſs of the <hi>beardleſs Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I muſt confeſs I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Down is ſtill upon his own Chin, or no; but if not, I muſt needs tell him, that for ought I find in his friendly <hi>half Sheet of Paper,</hi> the Beard contibutes no more to the making of the <hi>Divine,</hi> than it do's to the making of the <hi>Philoſopher;</hi> and therefore, I ſhall conclude with one piece of Advice to him, and that which may do him more true Service than all he has given the Confuter can ever do him, and that is, That, if it be really his hard fate not to be able to write more to the purpoſe, than what he has hitherto done, he would give over writing in this kind, and for the future follow the bent of his Genius, which ſeems to lead him rather to the Comical Humour of the Stage, than into the <hi>Field of Controverſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97405:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
